Guide to the James Fenimore Cooper Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1813-1894; Series I; 5.42; (13 boxes)
  - General Correspondence
    - Anonymous letters to Cooper, 1823-1844, undated (Box 10, Folder 275)
      15 AL
    - Miscellaneous "A-Z", 1927-1951 (Box 10, Folder 276)
      21 ALS to Cooper, unidentified MS
    - Envelope addressed to James Edward Root, undated (Box 10, Folder 277)
    - Letters regarding the election of Cooper to various societies, 1835-1850 (Box 10, Folder 278)
      18 ALS
    - Form letters, printed announcements, etc. addressed to Cooper, undated (Box 10, Folder 279)
    - Letters to Cooper requesting autographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 280-281)
      59 ALS
    - Letters to Cooper requesting him to lecture, 1832-1848 (Box 10, Folder 282)
    - Rough drafts of unfinished letters by Cooper, 1831-circa 1842 (Box 10, Folder 283)
      4 AL, including one note to General Lafayette
    - Letters regarding the Cooper libel suit, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 284)
      1 TLS to Ethel Rose Outland
      1 TLS to H. W. Boynton
    - Unidentified material, undated (Box 10, Folder 285)
  - Family Correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically under recipient and then by sender.
    - Cooper, Anne Charlotte Fenimore (daughter)
      - Bernard, Laura, 1830-1848 (Box 11, Folder 286)
        26 ALS
      - Cooper, Alice, undated (Box 11, Folder 287)
      - Cooper, Hannah C., 1843-1844 (Box 11, Folder 288)
      - Cooper, Paul Fenimore, 1839-1849 (Box 11, Folder 289)
        21 ALS to his sisters (chiefly Anne Charlotte Fenimore Cooper)
      - Cooper, Susan De Lancey, 1827-1831 (Box 11, Folder 290)
        Includes letters from Susan De Lancey Cooper to all of her daughters
      - Cooper, Susan Fenimore, 1834 (Box 11, Folder 291)
      - Cooper, Susan Maria, 1844, undated (Box 11, Folder 292)
      - De Lancey, Martha, undated (Box 11, Folder 293)
      - Disbrow, Ann, signed "Old Nurse", undated (Box 11, Folder 294)
        Includes letters written for Disbrow by her grandaughter Susan Ann Burrell
      - Laight, E. Watts, 1844-1845, undated (Box 11, Folder 295)
        27 ALS to Cooper
      - Maitland, Charlotte, 1841-1842 (Box 11, Folder 296)
        5 ALS to Cooper
      - Phinney, Elihu, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 297)
        Includes letters to Margaret De Lancey
      - Shubrick, William Branford, 1851 (Box 11, Folder 298)
      - Various correspondents, 1830-1839, undated (Box 11, Folder 299)
    - Cooper, Isaac (brother)
      - Conant, G.C., 1814 (Box 11, Folder 300)
    - Cooper, Maria Frances (daughter)
      - Cooper, Susan De Lancey, undated (Box 11, Folder 301)
        See also: Cooper, Susan De Lancey
    - Cooper, Paul Fenimore (son)
      - Brown, Thomas, 1852 (Box 11, Folder 302)
      - Clarke, C. C., 1847-1857 (Box 11, Folder 303)
      - Cooper, Anne Charlotte Fenimore, undated (Box 11, Folder 304)
      - Cooper, James Fenimore, 1845-1850 (Box 11, Folder 305)
      - Cooper, Richard, 1851-1855 (Box 11, Folder 306)
        65 ALS
      - Cooper, Susan De Lancey, circa 1844 (Box 11, Folder 307)
        1 ALS with a postscript in the handwriting of James Fenimore Cooper
      - Cooper, Susan Fenimore, 1831-1856 (Box 11, Folder 308)
        19 ALS
        Includes letter to Mary Fuller Barrows Cooper
      - Wynne, Dr., undated (Box 11, Folder 309)
        1 AL
      - De Lancey, E.C., 1842-1852 (Box 11, Folder 310)
        Includes letters to Anne Charlotte Fenimore Cooper
      - De Lancey, Edward, 1843-1856, undated (Box 11, Folder 311)
        63 ALS and 2 manuscript notes
      - Foot, Z. Charles, 1852 (Box 11, Folder 312)
      - Hand, George E., 1851-1852 (Box 11, Folder 313)
      - Phinney, Caroline Cooper, undated (Box 11, Folder 314)
        1 ALS, 1 ANS
      - Phinney, Elihu, 1855-1857 (Box 12, Folder 315)
      - Phinney, Henry Frederick, 1851-1857 (Box 12, Folder 316)
        41 ALS, 1 ANS
      - Rochester, Margaret, 1852 (Box 12, Folder 317)
      - Rochester, Thomas F., 1851-1852, undated (Box 12, Folder 318)
        9 ALS to Cooper and 1 document
      - Van Wagenen, G. G., 1846-1847 (Box 12, Folder 319)
      - Ward, Charles, 1854-1855 (Box 12, Folder 320)
      - Wood, James B., 1850-1854 (Box 12, Folder 321)
      - Various correspondents, 1817-1872 (Box 12, Folder 322-323)
        Includes certificate granting Cooper the right to practice law (1850 July)
    - Cooper, Richard (nephew)
      - Cooper, James Fenimore, 1833-1836 (Box 12, Folder 324)
      - Pell, Duncan, 1844 (Box 12, Folder 325)
      - Various Correspondents, 1841-1861 (Box 12, Folder 326)
        Includes copies of outgoing correspondence made by Cooper
    - Cooper, Susan De Lancey (wife)
      - Cooper, James Fenimore, 1812-1851, undated (Box 12, Folder 327-333)
        189 ALS
        Includes lock of JFC's hair from 1851
      - Cooper, Paul Fenimore, 1841-1851 (Box 13, Folder 334)
        23 ALS
      - Cooper, Susan Fenimore, 1831-1849, undated (Box 13, Folder 335)
      - Cruger, Harriet Douglas, 1839, 1845 (Box 13, Folder 336)
        1 ALS to Susan De Lancey Cooper and 1 ALS to Anne Charlotte Cooper
      - De Lancey, John Peter, 1812-1824, undated (Box 13, Folder 337)
        4 ANS from De Lancey and 1 ALS to De Lancey
      - De Lancey, Caroline, 1826-1832 (Box 13, Folder 338-339)
        1 ALS from Martha De Lancey
        93 ALS to Martha and Caroline DeLancy
      - De Lancey, Mary Ellison, 1839, undated (Box 13, Folder 340)
        Includes letters to Susan Fenimore Cooper and Anne Charlotte Fenimore Cooper
      - De Lancey, Thomas, 1847, 1851 (Box 13, Folder 341)
        Includes letter from Thomas De Lancey Jr.
      - De Lancey, William Heathcote, 1830-1856 (Box 13, Folder 342)
        13 ALS from De Lancey and 1 ALS to De Lancey
        Includes letters to Susan Fenimore Cooper and Paul Fenimore Cooper
      - Erving, Emily S., 1840-1842 (Box 13, Folder 343)
      - McAdam, Ann Charlotte, 1840, undated (Box 13, Folder 344)
        Includes letter to James Fenimore Cooper
      - Phinney, Caroline Cooper, undated (Box 13, Folder 345)
      - Pomeroy, Ann Cooper, circa 1833 (Box 13, Folder 346)
        1 ALS to Ann Pomeroy
      - Shubrick, Harriet Cordelia Wethered, 1839 (Box 13, Folder 347)
      - Various correspondents, 1827-1868, undated (Box 13, Folder 348)
        Letters from friends in France, Germany, and U.S.
      - Cooper, Susan Fenimore (daughter)
        - Baird, Spencer F., 1850-1851 (Box 13, Folder 349)
        - Bentley, Richard, 1851 (Box 13, Folder 350)
          1 ALS to Bentley
        - Bloss, Ann, undated (Box 13, Folder 351)
        - Bryant, William Cullen, 1854 (Box 13, Folder 352)
        - Carey, Hart & Co., 1849 (Box 13, Folder 353)
          1 ALS to Carey
        - Clymer, W.S., 1851 (Box 13, Folder 354)
        - Cooper, James Fenimore, 1830-1850 (Box 13, Folder 355)
        - Cooper, Susan De Lancey, 1827-1834 (Box 13, Folder 356)
        - De Kay, James E., 1849-1851 (Box 13, Folder 357)
        - Francis, John W. (John Wakefield), 1851 (Box 13, Folder 358)
          3 ALS to Francis
        - G.P. Putnam & Co., 1850 (Box 13, Folder 359)
          1 ALS to Putnam
          Includes note by James Fenimore Cooper
        - Griswold, Rufus Wilmot, 1851 (Box 13, Folder 360)
        - Hill, William, 1853 (Box 13, Folder 361)
        - H.O. Houghton & Company, 1872 (Box 13, Folder 362)
          Includes letters from H.F. Phinney
        - Jay, William, 1854 (Box 13, Folder 363)
          1 ALS to Cooper
        - Laight, E. Watts, undated (Box 13, Folder 364)
        - Phinney, Caroline Cooper, 1852, undated (Box 13, Folder 365)
          1 ANS and 2 ALS
          Includes letters addressed to all of her sisters
        - Putnam, George Palmer, 1851-1852 (Box 13, Folder 366)
        - Shubrick, William Branford, 1859, 1865 (Box 13, Folder 367)
        - Steinmetz, Madame, 1833 (Box 13, Folder 368)
          1 ALS to Steinmetz
          Includes notes by other family members
        - Various correspondents, 1857-1876 (Box 13, Folder 369)
        - Various recipients, 1832-1894 (Box 13, Folder 370)
          Letters to various extended family members
      - Phinney, Caroline Cooper (sister)
        - Cooper, Susan De Lancey, 1848 -1851 (Box 13, Folder 371)
          Includes 1 ALS to Henry Frederick Phinney
        - De Lancey, Martha A., 1833 (Box 13, Folder 372)
          1 ALS from Phinney
        - Shubrick, William Branford, 1865-1867 (Box 13, Folder 373)
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically by recipient
    - Campbell, Robert from James Dexter, 1847 (Box 13, Folder 374)
    - Cody, Daniel, signed agreement to publish withdrawal of charges against the character of James Fenimore Cooper, 1841 (Box 13, Folder 375)
    - Cooper, William from Hannah Cooper Pomeroy, 1888 (Box 13, Folder 376)
    - De Lancey, Peter from his nephew, 1803 (Box 13, Folder 377)
    - Fonda, Schuyler Crippin from J. Watson Webb, 1841 (Box 13, Folder 378)
    - Hoit, W.H. from Albert Gallatin Hoit, 1830 (Box 13, Folder 379)
    - Phinney, Henry Frederick from William Branford Shubrick, 1860 (Box 13, Folder 380)
    - Placide, Thomas from S.W. Lewis, 1853 (Box 13, Folder 381)
    - Willis, N.P. from Fanny de la Barca Calderon, 1846 (Box 13, Folder 382)
- Writings, 1824-1976; Series II; 3.34; (9 boxes)
  The series is organized into four subseries: Major Works; Essays; Other Writings; and Writings of Others.
  The series documents James Fenimore Cooper's writing career from the late 1820s until his death in 1851. While the papers do not include drafts for some of his better known novels, the series does contain material from a number of his writing projects, including several novels, articles, and essays.
  The series is comprised of documents from various stages of his writing process, from notebooks and drafts to printed versions and reviews. Following Cooper's death many of his manuscripts were dismantled and distributed to autograph collectors; as a result, many of the drafts here are incomplete. Major Works consists of Cooper's novels and non-fiction writings. Essays includes articles, such as Cooper's "Elaborate Review," regarding the proceedings of the naval court martial of Alexander Mackenzie. Other Writings includes contracts, fragments, and letters to the editor; published versions of Cooper's letters to the editor can also be found in Printed Material, Series III.
  The subseries Writings of Others contains academic scholarship on Cooper, as well as work by Cooper's grandson and a critique by Mark Twain. Also present is an essay by Cooper's daughter, Susan Fenimore Cooper, and comic book adaptations from the 1940s of James Fenimore Cooper's novels.
  - Major Works
    - Afloat and Ashore: or, The Adventures of Miles Wallingford
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, volume 1, chapter 28, 8 pages numbered "217-224", before 1844 (Box 14, Folder 383)
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, volume 1 (including preface), pages 1 through 119 (without pages 47 and 88), before 1844 (Box 14, Folder 384)
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, volume 2, chapters 16-23 (published as chapters 1-8), pages 121-184, before 1844 (Box 14, Folder 385-388)
      - Page proofs, corrected in unidentified handwriting, volumes 1 and 2, 1844 (Box 15, Folder 389-390)
        Volume 1: pages iii-vi; 7-236, lacking 28 pages
        Volume 2: pages 3-268, lacking 2 pages
    - The Bravo: A Venetian Story
      - Printed version, annotated, and interleaved with the author's holograph corrections, additions, and revisions for reissue in Bentley's Standard novel series, 1831 (Box 16, Folder 391)
        Volumes 1 and 2 of 3 volumes (published in London by Henry Colburn)
    - The Headsman
      - Draft fragment, holograph, chapter 14, before 1843 (Box 17, Folder 392)
      - Draft, holograph, 2 pages from chapters 30 and 31, before 1843 and 1874
        Includes ALS from Paul Fenimore Cooper to Dr. J.S. Mosher (1874 May 23) sending leaf as autograph
    - The Heidenmauer: or, The Benedictines
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, incomplete, before 1832
    - The History of the Navy of the United States of America
      - Correspondence, 1825-1843 (Box 17, Folder 393)
        Contains letters from Redmond Conyingham, George Henry Preble, J. Norris, and George D. Read
      - Notebook used in writing of various books on naval history, contains notes on commanders of vessels, battles, ships, and historical events, before 1839 (Box 17, Folder 394)
      - "Private Armed Vessels" notebook containing lists of vessels used in the war of 1812-1815, the revolutionary war, 1775-1778, and the war with France, 1758, before 1839 (Box 17, Folder 395)
        Several leaves torn out of the front and back
      - Notes on naval matters and personnel, before 1839 (Box 17, Folder 396)
        Not in Cooper's hand but information collected by him for use in The History of the Navy of the United States of America
      - Notes on naval officers and ships, before 1839 (Box 17, Folder 397)
      - Diagrams and notes of naval battles in the war of 1812, before 1839 (Box 17, Folder 398)
    - Home as Found
      - Reviews reprinted in The New Yorker and articles on the libel case against Webb, printed versions, 1839
      - "Webb's Indictments," Courier and Enquirer, printed version, 1840 September 18
    - Homeward Bound
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1838 (Box 17, Folder 399-407)
    - Jack Tier; or, The Florida Reef
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, volume 1, pages 20-34, 1848 (Box 17, Folder 408)
    - Notions of the Americans: Picked Up By a Travelling Bachelor
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, before 1828 (Box 18, Folder 409-410)
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, article comparing England with the U.S. and replying to criticism of Notions of Americans, undated (Box 18, Folder 411)
    - The Oak Openings; or, The Bee-Hunter
      - Draft fragment, holograph, before 1848 (Box 18, Folder 412)
    - The Pathfinder
      - Contract between James Fenimore Cooper and Richard Bentley, 1839 (Box 18, Folder 413)
    - The Pilot
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, preface for the 1849 revised edition (Box 18, Folder 414)
    - The Pioneers; or, The Sources of the Susquehanna: A Descriptive Tale
      - "The Harp of the Lake: Poetical Musings Upon Lake Otsego by Sydney," notebook, holograph, 1830 (Box 18, Folder 415)
        Dedicated to "Mrs. Dix" and dated "Cooperstown, August 27, 1830"
        Verse paraphrases of scenes from The Pioneers followed by miscellaneous poems
    - The Prairie
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, introduction, chapters 4-8, 10-34, incomplete, before 1827 (Box 18, Folder 416-427)
      - Draft, holograph, in hand of an amanuensis with corrections by Cooper, chapters 14, 20-25, 27-34, incomplete, before 1827
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, preface written for the new, revised edition published by Richard Bentley, London, 1832 (Box 18, Folder 428)
    - The Redskins: or, Indian and Injin: Being the Conclusion of the Littlepage Manuscripts
      - Draft, incomplete, holograph, corrected, before 1846 (Box 18, Folder 429-430)
        Includes preface; note by the editor; and pages 84-233 (missing pages 86-88 and 93)
    - The Red Rover
      - Draft, incomplete, holograph, corrected, revised preface for the Works of James Fenimore Cooper (New York: George P. Putnam, 1849-1850) (Box 18, Folder 431)
    - Satanstoe; or, The Family of Littlepage
      - Draft fragment, holograph, corrected, before 1845, 1876 (Box 18, Folder 432)
        Includes letter to Joseph Knight from Henry Coates (1876) and engraving of Cooper
    - The Towns of Manhattan
      - Draft fragment, holograph, corrected, partly in the handwriting of Anne Charlotte Fenimore Cooper, circa 1851 (Box 19, Folder 433)
      - Proofs, corrected, incomplete, circa 1851 (Box 19, Folder 434)
        Saved from the Putnam fire that destroyed the majority of the work
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, in the hand of Susan Fenimore Cooper for a proposed edition of those portions of the original book saved from the Putnam fire, circa 1851 (Box 19, Folder 435)
    - The Water Witch; or, The Skimmer of the Seas
      - Draft, incomplete, holograph, corrected, before 1830 (Box 19, Folder 436)
      - Draft fragment, holograph, in the handwriting of an amanuensis, with corrections by Cooper, chapters IV, V, VII, before 1830 (Box 19, Folder 437)
      - Draft fragment, holograph, corrected, before 1830 and 1885 (Box 19, Folder 438)
        Includes letter regarding the fragment to David F. Day from the former owner Charles K. McHarg (1885)
      - Documents concerning the Neapolitan censorship of The Water Witch, 1830 (Box 19, Folder 439)
        Addressed to Dr. Carlo Bonaparte
      - Review in Graham's Magazine, circa 1851 (Box 19, Folder 440)
    - The Ways of the Hour
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, before 1850 (Box 19, Folder 441-442)
  - Essays
    - "The Autobiography of a Pocket Handkerchief," agreement between George Graham and James Fenimore Cooper, 1842 September 24 (Box 19, Folder 443)
    - "Elaborate Review," Proceedings of the Naval Court Martial in the Case of Alexander Mackenzie, 1843-1844 (Box 19, Folder 444)
      Includes copies of official letters of Commodore John Rogers (March-October 1811); memoranda regarding the Mackenzie case possibly written by William H. Norris (undated); unsigned letters possibly sent from William H. Norris to Cooper (December 1843); and six diagrams of the battle of Lake Erie
    - "Hints on Manning the Navy," printed version, The Naval Magazine, 1836 March (Box 19, Folder 445)
    - "No Steamboat: A Vision," draft, holograph, corrected, incomplete, before 1843
      Previously titled "America: A Vision"
    - "Old Ironsides," drafts, corrected and printed version, Putnam's Monthly, before 1853 and 1853 (Box 20, Folder 446-447)
      Includes draft of pages 1-20 and 25-39 and copy probably in the handwriting of Susan Fenimore Cooper of the final portion of the article (pages 41-63)
    - "Resources of the American Navy," printed version, The Naval Magazine, 1836 January (Box 20, Folder 448)
    - "Reply to Captain Mackenzie's Criticism," draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1843 (Box 20, Folder 449)
      Possibly published as The Battle of Lake Erie, or Answers to Messrs. Burges, Duer, and Mackenzie
    - "Sketches of Naval Men: Melancthon Taylor Woolsey," printed version, Graham's Magazine, 1845 (Box 20, Folder 450)
  - Other Writings
    - Letter to Samuel Lewis Southard defending and explaining the conduct of Captain Isaac Chauncey, draft, holograph, corrected, 1827 October 28 (Box 20, Folder 451)
    - Letters to the editor, drafts, holograph, corrected regarding the Battle of Lake Erie and the criticisms of Cooper's account of it, circa 1842 (Box 20, Folder 452)
    - Letter to "Messrs. Editors" regarding naval history, 1853 (Box 20, Folder 453)
    - "To the Editor of The Edinburgh Review ," draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 20, Folder 454)
      Includes unidentified, draft fragment possibly from Cooper's review of Captain Basil Hall's Travels in America (1829) or Cooper's reply to the editor of The Edinburgh Review in repsonse to that journal's unfavorable review of Notions of Americans
    - "Fragments From a Diary of James Fenimore Cooper," printed version, Putnam's Magazine, 1868 June (Box 20, Folder 455)
      Diary excerpts from 1830
    - "Mr. Cooper Owns Copyright Of," single page in unidentified handwriting, listing twenty books by Cooper, after 1846 November (Box 20, Folder 456)
    - Notes dealing with parts of a manuscript sent to his publishers, Colburn and Carey. Written on the back of an envelope, undated (Box 20, Folder 457)
    - Contract with Charles Wiley, Abijah Weston, and James Fenimore Cooper for Lionel Lincoln, 1824 November (Box 20, Folder 458)
    - Contract with George R. Graham, entirely in Cooper's handwriting, with his signature and signed by G.R. Graham and R.W. Griswold, 1844 April 9 (Box 20, Folder 459)
    - Contract with George R. Graham and Company, 1846 June 3 (Box 20, Folder 460)
    - Unidentified, draft fragments, holograph, some in handwriting of Susan and Richard Cooper, undated (Box 20, Folder 461)
  - Writings of Others
    - Baldensperger, Fernand, "James Fenimore Cooper in France," The American Society Legion of Honor Magazine, printed vesion, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 462)
    - Beard, James Franklin, "James Fenimore Cooper," reprinted from Fifteen American Authors Before 1900: Bibliographic Essays on Research and Criticism, printed version, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 463)
    - Beard, James Franklin, "James Fenimore Cooper Aids Collectors," Manuscripts, printed version, 1953 (Box 21, Folder 464)
    - Beard, James Franklin, "The First History of Greater New York: Unknown Portions of Fenimore Cooper's Last Work," The New-York Historical Society Quarterly, printed version, 1953 (Box 21, Folder 465)
    - Various clippings about James Franklin Beard and his work on Cooper, 1960-1976 (Box 21, Folder 466)
    - Collier, John, "James Fenimore Cooper's Leatherstocking ", script, printed version, undated (Box 21, Folder 467)
    - Comic book adaptations of The Last of the Mohicans (Long Beach, N.Y.: Long Island Independent); The Spy (New York: Gilberton Company); and The Prairie (New York: Gilberton Company), 1943-1949 (Box 21, Folder 468)
    - Cooper, James Fenimore (Cooper's grandson), "Bibliography of James Fenimore Cooper," typescript, 1912 (Box 21, Folder 469)
    - Cooper, James Fenimore (Cooper's grandson), "Letters to James Fenimore Cooper, 1813-1850, and Some Unpublished Documents," typescript, 1922 (Box 21, Folder 470-471)
    - Cooper, Susan Fenimore, "Oneida: A Sketch," drafts, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 22, Folder 472)
    - De Witt, R.V., "The Annesley System of Naval Architecture," The New York State Mechanic, printed version, 1842
    - Fackenthal, Dr. B.F., "Col. Arthur Erwin and James Fenimore Cooper's Novel 'Wyandotte or the Hutted Knoll,'" Bucks County Historical Society Papers, 1922 (Box 22, Folder 473)
    - Kimball, Richard, "J. Fenimore Cooper," Century Magazine, 1881 (Box 22, Folder 474)
    - Leeds, Gurdon J., "Report of the Nautical Committee of the American Institute on Annesley's System of Ship Building," printed version, 1843
    - New York History, containing "The James Fenimore Cooper Sesquicentennial Celebration Exercises," printed version, 1941 (Box 22, Folder 475)
    - Spiller, Robert, "Fenimore Cooper: Critic of His Times: New Letters from Rome and Paris, 1830-31," Reprinted from American Literature, 1929 (Box 22, Folder 476)
    - Spiller, Robert, "Fenimore Cooper and Lafayette: Friends of Polish Freedom, 1830-1832," Reprinted from American Literature, 1935 (Box 22, Folder 477)
    - Spiller, Robert and Philip Blackburn, Descriptive Bibliography of the Writings of James Fenimore Cooper, background material and notes, before 1934
    - Twain, Mark, "Fenimore Cooper's Literary Offences," North American Review, printed version, 1895 July (Box 22, Folder 478)
    - Wallace, David, "The Princess and The Bravo ," The New-York Historical Society Quarterly, printed version, 1953 (Box 22, Folder 479)
    - WAMBA, "Reply to Cooper's Attack Upon Sir Walter Scott," The New Yorker, 1838 December 29
- Personal Papers, 1792-1975; Series III; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  The series is organized into six subseries: Diaries and Notebooks; Legal Records; Financial Records; Other Papers; Printed Material; and Clippings.